Finding Aids to Personal Papers and Special Collections in the VMFA Archives Lillian Thomas Pratt Personal Papers, 1901-1947 SC-07
VMFA Archives, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts
- Series 2: Hammer Galleries, 1933-1945, undated; SC-07-02
  - Series 2.3: Item Descriptions, 1933-1945, undated; SC-07-02.3
    - Florentine Renaissance Bust, Jan, 1945 (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - 5324, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - 5454, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - 5523, 5524, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - 5846, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - A68, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - A105, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - H3825, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - Easter Eggs, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - Imperial Russian Easter Egg 1896, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - Two Miniatures, 1896 Imperial Russian Easter Egg, 2272-1, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - Two Miniatures, 1896 Imperial Russian Easter Egg, 2272-2, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - Two Miniatures, 1896 Imperial Russian Easter Egg, 2272-4, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
    - Two Miniatures, 1896 Imperial Russian Easter Egg, 2272-6, undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 10)
  - Series 2.4: Exhibition Labels, 1933-1934, undated; SC-07-02.4
    - "Photograph of the daughters…", Oct. 2, 1933 (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 11)
    - "Linen handkerchief…", Oct. 2, 1933 (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 11)
    - "Solid gold column…", Jan. 4, 1934 (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 11)
    - "Silver plaque…", Jan. 4, 1934 (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 11)
    - "Icon delicately painted…", Jan. 4, 1934 (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 11)
    - "Silver teapot…", Jan. 4, 1934 (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 11)
    - "Heart-shaped box…", undated (Box SC-07 Box 1, Folder Folder 11)
  - Series 2.5: Correspondence, 1939; SC-07-02.5
    - Lady Constance Harriet Stuart Gaskell to Pratt, May 27, 1939 (Oversize SC-07 Oversize 1)
- Series 3: Estate, 1932-1947, undated; SC-07-03
  Box 2 (3 Folders and 1 Binder): This series is comprised of information about Pratt’s estate after her death on July 21, 1947. The estate tax return outlines the extent of her entire estate, including the varied philanthropic bequests and funds she had arranged. Detailed inventories of the estate list her belongings by category. One of the paintings lists was annotated by a local appraiser, Virginia Clarke Taylor, denoting which paintings were “antiques” or not. Finally, there are many price tags from other non-Faberge purchases she made over the years. Most are from the New York department store B. Altman and Company, and detail her acquisitions of silver, lamps, fabric, vases, paintings, and other decorative items.
  The series is divided into three subseries: Series 3.1: Tax Information, 1947; Series 3.2: Inventory, 1947, n.d.; Series 3.3: Other Furnishings, 1932, n.d.
  - Series 3.1: Tax Information, 1947; SC-07.03.1
    - United States Estate Tax Return, July 12, 1947 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 12)
    - Memorandum of Articles Bequeathed to VMFA (5 copies), Aug. 20, 1947 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 12)
  - Series 3.2: Inventory, 1947, undated; SC-07-03.2
    - Inventory M1-M85, [Books and Miscellaneous], undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory P1-P131, [Paintings], undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory P1-P136, Paintings (Antique), undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory P3-P139, Paintings (Not Antique), undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory P1-P139, [Paintings, Annotated by Virginia Clarke Taylor], Sep. 6, 1947 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory F1-F256, Furniture (Antique), undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory F4-F257, Furniture (Not Antique), undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory F1-F257, [Furniture (All)], undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory F84-F257, [Furniture (All)], undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory S1-S111, [Silver], undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory S50-S104, [Silver], 6 copies, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory J1-J188, [Jewelry], undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory J159-172, [Jewelry], 6 copies, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
    - Inventory Estate, [8 Miscellaneous Items], 4 copies, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 13)
  - Series 3.3: Other Furnishings, 1932, undated; SC-07-03.3
    - B. Altman, 26853, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 149322, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 159619, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 101/4062, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 353/13122, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, S1108, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 16/640, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 94/203, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 94/407, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 100/14, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 100/101, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 139/10211, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 139/12015, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, Bloor Darby Long Tom Vase, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, Old Colebrookdale Vase, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 13/B, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 63/2398, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 93C, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 93C, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 97/5043, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 191, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 191, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 191, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 191, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 44718, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, A917, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, A917, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, A922, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, A922, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, C3 93, 896 TL, D6199, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, C3 93, 896 TL, D6199, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/034F, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/7514, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/7515, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/7524, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/7524, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/7545, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/7547, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 301/7555, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 319/2182, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman Old Silver, 321/140, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 12/953, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 12/953, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 12/989, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 97/5043, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 5203, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 10346, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 10640, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 11370, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 11696, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 12875, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, 13698, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, Price Sticker, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, Blank Tag, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - B. Altman, Blank Tag, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Miller and Rhoads, 393B2, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Lord and Taylor, E-10 2212, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - J. E. Caldwell, Old Silver Tray, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - J. Parker and E. Wakelin, Sauce Boat, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - McCutcheon's Upholstery Department, S91, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 236, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 237-E, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 243, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 286, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 295, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, D1215, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, D1234, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, D1361, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, D1369, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 1353B, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 1353B, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 4537, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 307, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 2398/L, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 10679, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 301/7523, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 2886, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 2002, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, D1244, undated (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - Unknown, 39032 (2 tags attached together), Feb. 26, 1932 (Binder SC-07 Binder 1)
    - S. and G. Gump item description, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 14)
- Series 4: Clippings, 1932-1937, undated; SC-07-04
  Box 2 (1 Folder): This series is comprised of the few clippings that were found in the collection. As none of these particular clippings were mentioned in the correspondence directly, it’s possible that they did not originally belong to Pratt. The photographic copies of some of the articles were obviously made much later, but were retained as they may have been copies of articles Pratt once kept.
  - "Royal Russian Treasures," Richmond News Leader (2 copies), Apr. 20, 1932 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 15)
  - "Czarist Treasures to be seen in the Lobby of the Jefferson Hotel," Richmond Times-Dispatch (2 copies), Apr. 24, 1932 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 15)
  - "Romanoff Gems, Art Shown Here," Aaron Marc Stein, New York Evening Post, Jan. 3, 1933 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 15)
  - "Grand Duchess Victoria Dead," United Press, New York Herald Tribune, Mar. 3, 1936 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 15)
  - [Image of beverage urn], New York Sun, Oct. 16, 1937 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 15)
  - "Faberge Royal Craftsman," Ethel Walton Everett, Source unknown, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 15)
- Series 5: Museum Records, 1901-1947, undated; SC-07-05
  Box 2 (1 Folder): This series is comprised of items related to the Pratt collection that were transferred from the Curatorial department. Items found in the object records include early photographs of items from both Hammer Galleries and the Schaffer Collection, photographs of the Russian imperial family, as well as a statement of account from Hammer and the first complete list of the collection after its arrival at the museum in 1947.
  - A $1,000,000 Worth of Easter Eggs, Nov. 22, 1937 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Schaffer Galleries, Item 258, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Schaffer Galleries, Item 259, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Schaffer Galleries, Item 264, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Schaffer Galleries, Item 322, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Schaffer Galleries, Item 402, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Schaffer Galleries, Item 404, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Schaffer Galleries, Items 733-738, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Envelope from Akron Studios to Russian Imperial Treasures, 15 W. 50th Street, Attn. Mr. Schaffer, [1936 or later] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Red Cross Easter Egg stand, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Lillian Thomas Pratt Collection, [1947?] (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Statement of Account with Hammer Galleries [copy], Aug. 10, 1947 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Rock Crystal Easter Egg by Carl Fabergé Postcard, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Imperial Family and Royal Relatives at Fredensborg, Eneberettiget, 1901 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Identification of People in the Fredensborg Photo, undated (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - The Imperial Family on the Yacht "Standart," Summer of 1908 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - The Empress at Peterhof, Photo by Anna Virubova, 1910 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - The Emperor and Alexei N. on the "Standart," Photo by the Empress, 1912 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)
  - Empress Alexandra, Peterhof, Photo by Anna Virubova, 1914 (Box SC-07 Box 2, Folder Folder 16)